So in the past, we knew the last video we had a look at what interfaces are and how
they help us to write those ideal types, so now in this video what we are going to do
is I told you that it was in the page hour 8 world that is where we can only have abstract
things in an interface that is calculated limitations of any kind are not allowed inside
interfaces but that changed that to a significant change in how we do things after
Java 8 was released and by the way Java 8 is considered to be one of the greatest versions
of Java 8 but in these because of the significant number of features that were introduced
along with Java 5 and other versions as well but Java 8 sets that all over here again
I'm going to keep you updated with what else changed in Java 8 but this was one of the
significant changes and this impacted interfaces right and that thing that state when that
I made that is interfaces, completing limitations of any kind are not allowed inside
interfaces but after Java 8 this changed into concrete implementations of certain
kind are now allowed inside interfaces obviously we'll just stick to this now that is because
now we're dealing with the Java 8 world that is complete implementations of certain
kind are allowed inside interfaces and what are those certain kind and why did they make
this change will take it through a real one example of it will be stuck and then something
will come to the list and now let's see when look at this interface human see so I might
get this stuff if we just have a look at this thought that humans should be able to breathe
heat and walk now after 500 years of humans being on mother earth or might have a change
of mind thought that now humans should be able in addition to being heat and wall they
should even be able to smile as well let's assume that about 500 years of human existence
humans were not humans did not know how to smile they were not able to smile but after
500 years already thought that okay now they should be able to smile as well just put
this method inside interface human if all might be were having a Java developer they
would have written code like this correct so now that is funny anything is vital until
you go down and this starts to break immediately this starts to break immediately and every
class for that matter which had implemented class or interface human starts to break
abruptly out of nowhere and why is that because suddenly these all subclasses of human
they have broken the contract which contract am I talking about the contract that says
all of the abstract methods of an interface need to be implemented in the subclass of the
subclass needs to be declared as abstract and the ones that are implemented on the methods
of the interface right they were working fine everything was honky and dory but then suddenly
right the school was working and it immediately starts to break because they broke the contract
the contract says all of the abstract methods of the interface need to be overridden but until
not three were overridden and this change came in after 500 years or in your case after two or
three years or six months for example how would you know something has changed at the top and I
would need to change that as well and think about it this is this was no smaller vector because
think about this code has been running with production live with production by clients running
applications a billion dollar applications and suddenly something broke just because someone had
a change of heart at or at the complete advantage of Java it doesn't work that way they would
have soon or equal for billions of drivers in return and that is why we see and see this
can always happen see because coding as it says it's like an evolution always evolves you have a
change of mind change of heart that as you want to add certain things to an interface later on as
well and that is why this will not possible before Java because the contract would not be broken
when Java it they they introduce something for which allowed you to add to an interface later on
as well but still did not break a contract that's right and that was the introduction of default
methods or static methods in an interface and that is after Java 8 was released now for the first time
Java could have some concrete implementations in an interface and those were that is since Java 8.0 was
released now interface can also have default or static methods particularly precisely for this reason
to not let the subclasses suffer from no fault of this right now what happens is it's an interface
you can either put a default method that is with a body you're seeing this right and you're seeing
this line this is no dream that you're in that is an interface can now have concrete implementations
of certain kind but it's actually to avoid this kind of an embarrassment to a vehicle and that is
we can still add to an interface later on perfectly fine or I go on and do that but either use
the keyword default which was introduced in Java 8 or have the methodatic and now they can have
bodies they can't be abstract and now I'll say just as a reference to that say ended
starting Java and do you see this the contract did not break all those applications
millions of applications running lying after all these years the contract did not break
no errors they're still working fine in trade now they're still working in energy they're still
working over the subclasses that had already implemented the interface human before this was ended
and now you can edit without worrying about written the contract right and then it's such
rights because it's a normal concrete method it's a choice for energy it's a choice for shredder
and all those subclasses of human to whether to go on and override or smile around but they
have to worry about which way they would already do it but this is a choice so either they can have
the default or they can have stack static okay fine that's your choice right so from now I'll say
exactly for this because see the contract did not be the contract is only four abstract methods
they need to be over it in or the class needs to be cleared and subtract but not for default
or static methods for pretty fun and even mind motions because I promised that the start I keep
you updated what has changed in the recent words into Java to keep you updated with the language
and its ecosystem and there was one more change based on this change in Java 8 now they introduced
they said that now starting Java 9 now primary methods are also allowed inside interface
that is private default or private static methods right why does this change introduce
so that the abstract methods can share some data in between if they need to if they ever need
to do that in an interface right this one for exactly that right if you want to share some data
between those methods which are just within the interface right that is right that's a specified
private now it is allowed inside interface so these two with the significant changes made to the
language in Java 8 first Java 9 but this was much much more significant of that is either default
or static concrete methods are not now allowed inside interfaces and that makes me to the
conclusion that conclusion statement that is now certain concrete implementations are allowed
inside interface and I told you why we wasted and now it comes to the rescue and this allows us to
add to an interface later on as well